trained by day existential crisis by
night all day hello and welcome to the
next part of this conversation with John
for Vicki there's just a couple things
I'd like to tell you about it Before we
jump in and the first one is that this
is towards the more technical academic
side of the conversations that you'll
find here it's not my aim to have
conversations always of that nature in
this case I feel it's very much called
for as John is a genius-level thinker in
my humble opinion and I'm interested in
many of the same ideas and so for us to
really get where we could requires a
certain sort of dialogue that tends
towards the more academic side but that
won't be all you find here and it is a
very much intention of mine to speak in
a way that is more accessible and to
break down concepts when appropriate
rather than just always pull from
whatever tangent the unconscious seems
to be so that's the first thing and the
second thing is that even if you are
interested in a more academic style of
conversation you may have to put up with
the first five minutes of me talking
before we get to John I cut this
conversation in half it was initially
both parts 1 & 2 were had it on the same
in the same session and so the break is
somewhat artificial although the jump in
the conversation itself was quite abrupt
so even if you were to go listen to part
one beforehand the jump into the more
metaphysical component is still fairly
abrupt and yeah the first five minutes
are me feeling my way through setting
the context for a certain sort of
discussion and what you can expect to
hear is a discussion about consciousness
and you'll hear some of John's
metaphysical position with respect to
the ontological status of consciousness
I won't say too much more than that
yeah thank you very much and I look
forward to bringing you more content in
the future
okay so if you can bear with me and you
might have to help me along with this
because of our limited time remaining I
want to see if I can provide a context
for a particular sort of metaphysical
discussion so I can better understand
your position on things and sure to
share a little bit about how where my
not just interests but where my capacity
to make coherence of things currently
lies with and is to do with in some
important sense what's most fundamental
I suppose it's to do with ontology but
it's a process metaphysics where in
actually our agency and our capacity to
draw coherence into experience might be
used as an important vehicle to gain
insight into not just psychological
process of sense making and the
cognitive process of relevance
realization but perhaps to metaphysical
process itself and now there are some
shion's involved here that that I can
see things going different ways but for
example in one of your lectures you
talked about the importance or not the
importance you provide a very basic
schema of I think it goes something like
inorganic thing it's a living thing to
Aristotle's hierarchy yes Aristotle's
hierarchy to moving thing to mental
thing to cube the human thing which is
the rational thing or something like
this which is self reflective capacities
yeah the self motion eventually becomes
self reflection right yes so I'm not
sure whether or not that's I know you're
introducing these thinkers a lot to sort
of help provide a framework for thinking
about things in different ways and my
sense is that you have um you know you
have an affinity for each of these
thinkers in a different way and so I'm
not taking it that that is precisely
what you endorse metaphysically but
where I wrote where I get where I where
I'm interested in is because you you
speak a lot as well about the
the the co defining into the pendant
relationship between the agent and the
arena between the cognitive agent the
thing that makes sense of the world and
the environment as such so that the
closer you are to coming into touch with
that also the more real and more human
you become and that is this optimization
process associated with realizing the
meaning and realizing a closer fit
between yourself and the environment the
question is for this meaning making
process - because I agree with you it is
these practices attempting to come into
communion with these practices and not
getting lost in an autodidactic spiral
although by the way autodidactic spirals
are sometimes the only way you can come
into yourself enough so you can connect
with genuine community and there's
another tension there of course hmm is
that okay at what point like like one
issue I have is with this idea of a sort
of a radical emergence and I'm not
saying that you're that you're
necessitating we endorse this kind of
radical emergence from a from a holy non
meaningful non-sentient non capacity to
discern how to come into relationship
with there's this notion of goal right
there's this notion of becoming a more
actualized better fit so that what so
that more transformation can continue
and menses and it's a kind of loving
transformation right because it's an
it's an affirmation of self and the
world in some important sense in a way
that transforms it and there's also an
added an admission there that that we
are connected in fundamental ways that
together we come into these Co Co
defining Co interpretive transformations
and become something more connected more
real in some sense
well how fundamental is this process of
of transformation to what we must
endorse metaphysically in the world
itself we might be something to say how
fundamentalist sentience how
fundamentalist consciousness I find it
difficult to understand how this process
can kick
with the meaning associated the goal
formation associated even if it's
implicit this it gives coherence the
goals give coherence this relationship
to meet in kind of a unity of goals a
unity of becoming of harmonizing
evermore in this holistic way right it
seems to me like I can't understand how
this is not fundamental to being itself
at least as far as we can conceive it
psychologically and then the lighter
comes between psychological psychology
and metaphysics becomes blurred so I'm
interested in the role you think
something like this subjective coherence
making transformation plays in your
metaphysics is consciousness fundamental
is something like sentience fundamental
or is it an emergent property of
something that is non-sentient okay so
there's a lot of things there there's a
very complex question yes the first the
first thing is and I don't know how much
you're committed to some of your
predicates but I would argue that our
meaning is not subjective it's
transgender and part of the ontology
that I'm trying to advocate for is an
ontology of real relations right that
relations aren't just sort of mental
glue that we use to to to take to put
things together and I think that that is
actually something that is comports well
with our scientific ontology because
things like evolution are dynamical
systems themselves they're
self-organizing processes and I take it
that you do there's a general consensus
that evolution is the best explanation
of how we actually got here and if
therefore there has to be a reality to
it as a causal factor in our emergence
and therefore these dynamical systems
and the sets of constraints that and the
real relations that they embody are real
and causally efficacious and in an
important way so I take that to be a
fundamental thing and then once you give
me that in my ontology then I would talk
about I talk about two things first I
talk about it in terms of a deep
continuity hypothesis the idea that my
my friend and a colleague Evan Thompson
has developed out of the work of
Francisco Varela and others and this is
the idea and this actually comes out in
the relevant
realization theory this is the idea that
the the the system of constraints right
that structural functional organization
and this is this is very much the
Aristotelian model that makes me
possible as a biological agent that
right now those sets right of
constraints they get accepted they're
not identical they get exactly the way
my tongue has been exacted for speech
they get exact it up into cognition and
they get exact it up into other other
levels of our notion of self and that
there's a deep continuity between the
kind of self organizational processes we
find in the depths of our biology and
that we find in the height of our
reflective rationality and many people
are arguing for this deep continuity now
you may say well you know that gets me
sort of in that that I can sort of seed
right and that's a kind but that's only
taking me sort of into one layer of the
ontology well no because I think there's
also a deep continuity between being a
biological thing which is an auto poetic
thing a self organs are self-organizing
systems that are self organized to seek
out the conditions of their own
existence yes and that's how they differ
from merely self-organizing things like
tornados that do not self makes in a way
yeah yeah
so autopoietic is self making exactly
whereas the the tornado is only
self-organizing but there's of course
again continuity between what we see in
the in the self making seeking behavior
of of you know even a Paramecium and the
self-organization right capacity that we
see in the fire that is spreading so we
can with instead of just reading upwards
right you also should use your ontology
and read downwards you should see how
the upper-level thing gives you an
affordance of intelligibility down into
the depths of your ontology and then
that leads me to my second point now
this is not something I have as well
developed and so I ask for some charity
on the part of your your your listeners
but I
become increasingly sort of critical of
these two big things that we have tended
to do with our ontology we tend to have
a completely emergentist ontology in
which everything emerges up or if you go
back far enough in sort of the
Neoplatonic framework we have the exact
opposite we have a completely emanation
right ontology and I think both of these
ontology x' and perhaps I think I think
it could make a case that this is a
point that Whitehead was making so you
might find resonance with this both of
these ontological grammars a completely
emergentist and a completely emanation
esta count I think have like they each
have just you know they have obverse
sets of you know you know irresolvable
problems that they can't do and that
sort of points to me that either one of
these exclusive ways of thinking of our
ontology is in some fundamental way
flawed now and trying to get beyond both
emergence and emanation I think is one
of the central tasks facing us as people
are trying to understand our ontology
and that's why I like what I advocated
earlier about you know the deep
continuity hypothesis says don't only
look upwards like when you're trying to
understand like the emergence of
consciousness take the properties and
make that inform how you look downward
again make that a grammar of
intelligibility how you look downward
now you shouldn't simplistically then
say oh well that means that
consciousness is down at the fundamental
level because that is to miss exactly
right what the power of the emergentist
has said but you also should you
shouldn't think right that right that
there's some sort of dualistic heaven
that the emanation s wants you know the
land of the world of pure form and so I
as I said that second point I think is
something that we really I'm really
wrestling with it in my mind it
intersects with this deeper attempt I
have to try to get and break through a
lot of these dichotomies that sort of
have us locked in
an ineffective grammar of cognition and
of our existential lives so I don't know
if right I do know that that is in no
way a complete yes a responsible answer
but I'm trying to show you what my
thinking is about this no beautiful I
mean that's I mean that's all we can do
to begin with right and maybe that's all
we could do at the end which is just put
our frames of where we're at with this
stuff together it's obviously not so
it's not not not not some God getting to
the acute end of this stuff is not is
not easy um I wonder if one way to
progress the conversation from here is
to talk about the role that you might
take cognitive cognitive agents to play
or perhaps the role that consciousness
plays in the mediation of the potential
of potential into the actual mm-hmm is
the dynamic something that is
potentially one that can resolve this
problem with emergence and emanation I
hope so I mean I I I would I mean I have
argued that I've published and I'm
working on for a deep continuity between
the machinery of consciousness as a form
of relevance realization that is also
generating perspectival knowing right
and a salience landscaping and you know
what what consciousness does is it makes
it gives us this textured salience
landscape in which we're caught up in
sort of you know fields of obvious Ness
and so but I think that that at the core
and I make the argument this is
convergent with a lot of work at the
core of that as machinery of relevance
realization which I think ultimately is
continuous with the machinery of your
intelligence and and that's and you can
see that in how both consciousness and
at least your fluid intelligence are
deeply correlated with working memory
right and so you can see working memory
is a place where you know you can if
you'll allow me I don't not happy with
these metaphors but they're the ones
we're using you can sort of look up to
consciousness and you can look down to
the intelligence found in our cognition
and then you can look through that
intelligence right also into the
machinery of our
logical existence here's why I argue
explicitly that the relevance
realization that is at the core of your
intelligence is actually a function of
the bio economy of your brain it's it's
it's working in terms of you know the
logistical properties of efficiency and
resiliency that you know are
constitutive of any adaptive autopoietic
system and so that's what I mean I like
when if I if I I would argue not
everybody agrees with me of course so
that would be really ridiculously
pretentious but I would argue that if
you look at consciousness the right way
you can see continuity with intelligence
and then that very way of looking at
intelligence allows you to see
continuity down to life and then that's
a very Aristotelian framework again yes
well I think that's very interesting and
I can't participate in that conversation
with the degree of acuity that you have
for some of this although I think I'm
with you as far as the gestalt goes
still seems seems to me that there's
something about the process of
transformation mm-hmm which is
experienced experientially can be
discerned and oriented in experience
involves the the interplay of well
coherence and incoherence sure and that
there's something about that which which
yes I can see being well it can see
something's in some analogous way being
the process which enables self making
autopoietic systems you come into an
appropriate fusion with anything at all
so really what I'm just looking to argue
or get clear on is whether or not there
is like there has it seems to me there
should be a fitted napot ins of engaging
the consciousness that we have oh and
the and the processes which enable
coherence to be a fact of consciousness
at all in what we might traditionally
think
as non-conscious things I'm not acting
arguing for consciousness as we have it
at the bottom of things but just that
there is a kind of there is a kind of
sentience awareness and implicit goal
formulation and goal actualization and a
transformation occurring with
actualizing that goal which can be
understood in this some like some
ontology of the actual and the potential
and the mediation in-between and then
you have this kind of you have an engine
there of a becoming and a transformation
towards growth will be uses that terms
transcend and include there is this kind
of fusion that then baguettes a
different perspective it's nothing's
become something else but it's embraced
what was before and it's moving on and
developing and it is a genuine
aggression into novelty in some sense
and so it seems to like because I I
think what's important to so people get
stuck in a nihilistic worldview where
there's no meaning to anything
whatsoever right or they endorse some
ideology that that gives them meaning
right which might really just be some
sort of power position sure but but what
seems to me to be the case is that there
is at the at the core of you can be
destroyed in experience and we haven't
spoken about psychedelics this is
something that's very interesting and
meditation of course you're working with
the same machinery to you know um that
there is a it's like to get the whole
process of this thing that we're all
involved in this process that we're all
inexorably unceasingly existentially
trapped in or a part of and can
transcend by embracing is like are you
trapped in an ironic cycle of becoming
or do you embrace it and affirm it with
love at your core not just for self but
for everything right because self is
everything in some important sense but
so if a bit so if all is in koi for
there to be coherence between things
there is a pattern of at least that a
meta pattern of transformation that we
participate in where there is this kind
of connected becoming of love
transformation like like that it seems
to be a pattern for me that that can
make sense or it's something about that
fit so I'm drawn to say it that there's
something about how you can show up as
you in an attempt to transform yourself
with love for like an affirmation of
this cycle at your core that is is
something to draw on which which can
transform anybody its how metaphysically
a part of the very transformation of
being itself is that that's the point
I'm trying to how involved is the human
being in fundamental transformation of
the universe as such like if there's
this if there's this if there's this
coupling if there's this pattern
matching of the coherence we make in our
experience but also this sentient
awareness goal formation transformation
happening at the autopoietic level then
all of a sudden we participate in
something genuinely fundamental and it
seems to me the participation in
something fundamental has the right to
be called something spiritual and then
all of a sudden you have so okay I'll
stop there well and then and then there
we have the the human being as
participating in something fundamental
it's this capacity to recreate ourselves
by being in touch with what we most
authentically are as we can grip onto
the world as we can authentically feel
it that constitutes then this this
spirituality and this divine capacity to
be involved in the process of your own
own transformation and the
transformation of the world so I think I
understand what you're talking about
I guess here's what I would try to say
in response to that first I'll say what
I clearly don't agree with and then and
what I agree with and then we could
negotiate around it so I think trying to
understand this as it is a teleological
aspect of our metaphysics I think is is
I'm suspicious of that I think of that
as probably mistaken because of the
continued this continual pattern our
intelligibility has advanced reliably at
the expense of teleology right as sort
of at the fundamental ground of thing
so III would hesitate to express any of
this to theologically I would also I'd
again go back to thinking of like I said
of meaning as trans Jack give as a way
in which like like my biological fitted
disc I am fitted to the real patterns in
the environment that doesn't mean that
my fitness is a property of the
environment it's exactly right
it's it's a way in which the environment
at Dyea fit together and this is the
notion of affordance right the grass for
ability of the glass isn't a property of
the glass it isn't a property of my hand
it's a real relationship between my hand
and the glass and so I would think of
this in terms of real affordances you
know Ella Gibson and most of the people
in third generation card side and that
we genuinely need to bring in
affordances into our ontology of how
we're going to talk about cognitive and
and biological entities so I would I
would say that and then what I would
want to say and this is again I'm more
tentative and you know I've read quite a
bit of Whitehead myself as well and you
know and and a lot of Neoplatonism and
this idea you know that there there is a
there's a structure of intelligibility
to the world but I want to separate that
from any from any sort of TD illogical
movement or momentum but they're there
they're there is a way in which
possibility and actuality are are
organized that are deeply constitutive
of what we take to be the realness of
things and so when I'm talking about the
intelligibility of the cup right of the
glass you know and and this is where I I
think I I'm in agreement with you right
I'm talking not only about the structure
by which it's no one I'm also started
talking about the structure by which it
is right and that there's a level at
which the patterns of intelligibility
and the patterns by which that thing it
is organized to be the thing it is are
get into some kind of conformity with
each other now I don't mean that in the
old way that Aristotle meant but I think
there's a newer way of trying to
understand
which I'm trying to articulate with you
that I think does give us a sense of
that when I am right experiencing a kind
of you know sort of profound
connectedness and deep coherence of
intelligibility in my cognition that is
disclosing a kind of deep coherence and
intelligible structure to the universe
and that gives me a profound sense of
connectedness and meaning and I take
both of those poles to be real things
and the relation itself to be real so I
take the whole process to be real yes
yes I understand and I wonder if so I
wonder if you thinking what I put
forward before that my notion of
teleology is one that places a fixed
goal into the equation because I don't
think that's what I don't want to
endorse that there is an endpoint at all
to this idea of teleology and if it was
the so go ahead I know no I I guess for
me I mean we have to we have to try and
explicate the models we're using here
and and and they're always there so we
have the model of making like the
generation of artifacts and then we have
the the model of making that comes
through something like evolution and I
take it that the project of trying to
use the first model has largely failed
and that what we're talking about when
we're talking about the way the universe
is making creating bringing about
novelty you know sort of disclosing the
inexhaustibility of itself I take that
maybe when that that a better model I'm
not claiming identity but I think that a
better model for that is the
evolutionary model of of making rather
than the artefactual model of making yes
okay so where where I'm at in my
thinking what's being gripping me is
that is that what you know and it's
influenced by as far as I understand it
the Union notion of the god image the
image of self at the at the depths of
the psyche which is at once that which
is the ember of what drives and makes
libido possible and makes energy
possible and gets things moving but it's
also the the echo or the image that is
is projected but it's also chased but
that but this is just an this I mean and
I I'm not trying to do a disservice to
young but this is just a recapitulation
of Pro classes notion the great
neoplatonist of the one within and the
one without you know the the one of the
cosmos and the one of the psyche are you
know have a fundamental relationship to
each other and happiest Raman that kind
of thing - right for me it's really is
it also that actually you can have the
notion of Atman is Brahman like yes
that's everything and the idea that if I
get it sort of but you know but but I
have to
I think precisely what for let's take
for example both the Neoplatonic and the
and the vedanta you know traditions say
is if you claim me in to write a sort of
an autobiographical sense of trying to
get who you are and sort of your goal
seeking your and the teleology of your
existence you're actually gonna not come
into contact with that one and you're
not good at meant is right it's it's not
identical but non do all with brahman
and i think that that's the same idea I
think in some important ways I'm not
keeping a simplistic perennialism but I
think you're seeing a simple or our idea
right in the neo platonic tradition that
when I realize the one within when I get
that sort of that dynamic ground that
washburn when I get at that sort of that
that dynamic structural functional
organisation operating principles of who
of my psyche in total that gives me a
participatory knowing I know of sort of
the some of the operating principles you
know in the external world yes I think
that's that's deep right and it's the
sense in which I think you know Leonard
angel are is that ultimately has to be
the case and so if that's what we're
talking about
iiiiii yes I would I would say I would
support that
what what what I what what I'm
hesitating about is again we're trying
to think
of that one minute as anything analogous
to pili illogical products or endeavors
not that's what because I do think these
were these three things line up I think
the scientific worldview the neo
platonic and the Vedanta both point
towards no no that's what you have to
let go in order to get to that level we
find that that deep inner that eat deep
inner penetration I mean it what happens
I think and this is what I would make a
cognitive scientific argument for is you
get you get a kind of knowing that it's
disclosed and it's it's where they've
got between knowing and being dissolves
look III know I'm conscious by being
conscious to quote form it I know I
don't know I'm conscious by having
beliefs about my consciousness right I
don't know that I'm conscious by
creating theories about it I know it if
I ask you of your conscious right now do
you know you're conscious by being
conscious and I think there's other
things we know by being them rather than
thinking about them reflecting on them
or dis forcing about them yes yes I mean
the the relationship between these kinds
of knowing I think is absolutely crucial
and there's more there's so much more I
want to say and I think it would take
yeah a lot more time to to get clear on
where I'm coming from because I don't
have the depth of learning that you do
and I have I think I have in some sense
a a frame that's been stretched to
important dimensions that allows me a
container to play in the space but mu
you make caught you know to make
sensible the different diamonds in that
space is something that yes it takes me
many many you know attempts at
generating it and it would take us some
time and I'm conscious of two things one
is that we have a poor connection thing
here going on with Skype this last
couple minutes I think it's you oh you
had movements and energy if you've
interrupted their flow and the other one
is that I know
that we have about three minutes left so
I don't know how to wrap something like
this up because as far as I'm concerned
it's the beginning of a conversation and
it's one I've thoroughly enjoyed and
there's I'm happy I'm happy to come back
at some future date type someone I'd
love to I'd love to and you know I'd
actually like to discuss with you and
and others how to make that time most
effective partly because I have I have
two drives well - yeah at least two
drives with this kind of project right
one is one is what we've been doing for
the last half an hour which is to
genuinely explore at the limits of my
own understanding and to participate in
a conversation at that level and I think
there's value in that but I do I do too
but but the other is to the other is to
make the experience of meaningful
conversation available for as many
people as possible and I want to include
people in the participation in in
meaningful conversation world forums as
much as possible - if you would like to
set up a situation where you can bring
as you had done a couple posters but if
you want to have you know an interview
where you bring up like questions that
your wants to pose to me or something
like that I I will well I will make
myself available to that I take that
seriously awesome I will make myself
available to that I mean that you know
and if you want to do that you know in
the fair fairly near future
I'm open to that as long as we you know
coordinate schedules I'm very happy to
do that
I I do I want to I want to scaffold that
I want to share the responsibilities you
feel to your community I want to help
help that process as much as I can
beautiful well thank you John you know
I'll leave this conversation very very
happy to have met you and you I've done
it but also I can tell you I'm gonna
walk away being it's a little
bittersweet in knowing that there's some
other things about
that there's so many things left unsaid
and I think in some important because I
are a god I do feel there's this tension
there's it's it's probably just it's
partly just attention of it's just
attention of of language and in some
respects it's it's the very kind of
tension that's not served best by doing
this online writer there's this is
coming into touch with the importance of
of human being in the world and in some
important sense I feel a deep I deep
resonance and alignment with with what
you're doing and I I think that yeah I'm
very I'm very grateful for for all the
teaching that you've um that you've put
out there I'm very grateful for what
you've taught me and yeah I look forward
to continuing this conversation more and
throwing some more metaphysical things
out you in the future well hey I really
enjoyed this conversation I think this
is well easiest ones I've ever had
um and I I think you picked up on how
involved I God precisely for that reason
so deeply deeply enjoyed it I'm very
deeply enjoyed it I would very much like
I said I'd like to continue the
discussion at some further point eager
what we are doing actually not either
both what we're doing and like I said
make myself available with you as in
some form of mediator for addressing
questions because you know if other
people are meeting up and disconnect my
work I want them to feel that I bet I
will be responsible to their engagement
with my work I feel responsibility and I
want a venue in which I can I can I can
undertake to discharge a beautiful well
hopefully if things go well for the
project and I believe they will then
there will be events I can hold in the
future where we might even be able to
fly you out and and do something fun in
the years to come
I would like to see if that's possible
well that'd be great that'd be great
I mean I would love an excuse to come to
Australia yeah that's awesome well John
thank you very much and best of luck
with everything you're doing
thank you thank you so very much Tim I
look forward to us speaking again
all right doing
introduction on video and we're gonna do
it in one take
that's a lie I've done like 30
it's fine I've got I've got other things
to do but I'm it's all good
here we go doing an introduction on
video looking directly at the camera
lens like it's a human being like it's a
human being that I want to talk to and
smile at and not just sort of stew in
this weird self recursive